A Guide to the Secrets of the Sequence records, 2000-2007
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Secrets of the Sequence records 2000-2007
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
2013/Aug/68
67.6 linear feet, 52 record center boxes.
Virginia Commonwealth University. Office of the President.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research, except for subseries 1.4 which is restricted. Please consult the repository for details. To view the audiovisual materials in the collection please make an appointment to ensure the necessary equipment for viewing is available.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from Virginia Commonwealth University, Office of the President.
Historical Information
Secrets of the Sequence(SOTS) is an educational television series that aired on Public Television in 2002-2003. The show, a weekly TV news magazine hosted by Lucky Severson, was created to educate the public about current developments in genetics and life sciences,as well as the applications of the research from these fields. Ward Television Corporation produced the program in collaboration with six leading life sciences research institutions: Harvard University; Medical Research Council Laboratory of Molecular Biology (Cambridge, England); University of California, San Fancisco; University of Michigan; University of Wisconsin, Madison; and VCU. The project was funded in part by Oracle and the Pfizer Foundation. Each episode consisted of three, eight-minute segements which featured the work of scientists and researchers from the participating institutions. The show debued on April 7, 2002 and ran until March 2003 with a total of 52 episodes aired.
The idea for SOTS began at VCU due to President Eugene P. Trani's active support for the life sciences. He spearheaded the creation of VCU Life Sciences, a comprehensive program intergrating the School of Medicine, VCU Health System, the Inger and Walter Rice Center for Environmental Life Sciences, and programs in the sciences, engineering, business, education, and the humanities. This program was created to educate not only students, but the broader public as well to raise awarness about research and advancements in the Life Sciences. In 2001 VCU engaged the services of McGrath/Crossen Associates, a public relations firm, to find ways of promoting these ideas to the community at large and to raise the profile of the University. The concept of the show was created and other institutions were invited to join in the project. At a press conference in March 2002 to promote SOTS Dr. Trani stated that the series represented a "breakthrough in the effort to establish a public dialogue about the implications of research in a post-genomic era." He discussed the need for an informed society for the formation of responsible public policy on these issues and declared, "where the public goes, so goes the future of education and public policy."
Fifty of the best segments of the SOTS shows were adapted to assist teachers in the application of genetic research across the biology curriculum. These 8-10 minute videos were made available for free download through VCU. This project was funded by the Pfizer Foundation and the National Academy of Sciences. Additional funding from the Howard Hughes Medical Institution allowed for the creation of more videos which have been added to the site. Each video includes an accompanying classroom-tested lesson that encourages students to further explore the video topics. These vidoes can be found here
Scope and Content
The records of the Secrets of the Sequence (SOTS) television show, 2000-2007, are those created and collected by the Office of the President at VCU, which played a key role in the creation and production of this project. The records include correspondence, project and production information, video masters, b-roll footage, and other materials related to the creation and production of the television series.
Series 1: Administrative records, 2000-2007. This series consists of records relating to the development of the show and is divided into four subseries.
Subseries 1.1: Correspondence. This subseries includes printed copies of emails that were exchanged primarily between VCU, McGrath/Crossen Associates, Ward TV, and the other institutions involved in the show. Topics covered include the development of the concept, funding, production, and promotion of the show.
Subseries 1.2: Development of concept and publicity records. This includes materials such as the script for the series pilot, episode descriptions, press releases and details of the press conference held to promote the show, a progress report, a white paper on the neccesity for life sciences education, and other related materials.
Subseries 1.3: Participants. Materials include profiles of the six research institutions involved in the creation of SOTS, biographies of the members of those institutions who also served on the Board of Advisors, and other materials relating to the Life Sciences programs at those institutions.
Subseries 1.4: Legal records. This subseries contains arbitration testimony, materials regarding the Ward TV bankruptcy case, and materials related to a FOIA request by the Richmond Times Dispatch.
Series 2: Production records, 2001-2003. This series includes the production files for episodes 106-152 which contain scripts, location and crew releases, chyrons (television graphics that appear on the lower third of the screen), edit decision lists (EDS), and other materials related to the productio of SOTS. Also in this series are files containing personal, logo, location, and stock footage releases and a file of stills and slides.
Series 3: Videos, 2000-2003. This series contains the master tapes of SOTS and b-roll footage used for show segments. The majority of these are Betacam SP cassettes, but there are also VHS tapes, CDs, and DVCam cassettes. Some of the masters are PAL or International format. A link to the video inventory can be found here.
Arrangement
The Secrets of the Sequence records have been divided into three series with subseries as needed:
Series 1: Administrative records, 2000-2007
Subseries 1.1: Correspondence, 2001-2003
Subseries 1.2: Development of concept and publicity records, 2001-2006
Subseries 1.3: Participants, 2000-2003
Subseries 1.4: Legal records, 2002-2007
Series 2: Production records, 2001-2003
Series 3: Videos, 2000-2003
Efforts have been made to preserve the original order of these files where applicable. Series 2 has been kept in the exact order in which it was received. The videos have been placed in order by the six digit number found on all the videos except for those in box 52, which do not have a number.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Technical Requirements
The videos in Series 3 are in various formats. The majority are recorded on Sony Betacam SP cassettes. There are also some VHS tapes, Sony DVCam cassettes, and CDs. Screening will require proper equipment for playback. To view these materials please contact the repository for an appointment to ensure that the equipment is available.
Related Material
VHS copies of the Secrets of the Sequence episodes 101-133 are located in the media collections at VCU Libraries, call number QH430.S47 2002.
Contents List
- Administrative records, 2000-2007 (Box 1-2)
  - Correspondence, 2001-2003 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 2001-2003 (Box-folder 1:1-4)
    - Correspondence, mass email, 3/20/2002 (Box-folder 1:5)
      Draft of a mass email announcing the press briefing about the launch of Secrets of the Sequence and information on the recipients of the email.
    - Correspondence, Ward TV, 2001-2003 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Development of concept and publicity records, 2001-2006 (Box 1-2)
    - Emails, white papers, press releases, 2001-2003 (Box-folder 1:7)
    - General files, drafts, and notes, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 1:8-9)
    - McGrath/Crossen Associates, 2002-2003 (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Press Conference, Washington, D.C., 3/21/2001 (Box-folder 1:11)
    - Program pilot, 2001 (Box-folder 1:12)
    - Progress report, 2003 (Box-folder 1:13)
    - Project description, 2001 (Box-folder 1:14)
    - Episode descriptions, 101-141, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 1:15)
    - National Association of Biology Teachers, 2002 (Box-folder 1:16)
    - SOTS Videos and Accompanying Lesson Project, 2002-2006 (Box-folder 1:17)
    - VCU Life Sciences, 2001 (Box-folder 1:18)
    - VCU Life Sciences Career Guide, 2001 (Box-folder 2:1)
    - Vignettes, 2001 (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Why do we need public education in the Life Sciences?, 2002 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Participants 2000-2003 (Box 2)
    - Advisory Board, 2002-2003 (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Harvard Medical School, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 2:5)
    - MCR Laboratory of Molecular Biology, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 2:6)
    - University of California, San Francisco, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 2:7)
    - University of Michigan, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 2:8-9)
    - University of Wisconsin, Madison, 2000-2002 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Legal records, 2002-2007 (Box 2)
    - Arbitration testimony, 2003 (Box-folder 2:11-14)
    - FOIA request, 2002 (Box-folder 2:15)
    - Ward TV bankruptcy case, 2005-2007 (Box-folder 2:16)
- Production records, 2001-2003 (Box 2-9)
  - Episode 106: Facts of Life, Haseltine, The Diabetes Cure (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Episode 107: Sweet Genes, Broken Hearts, De-coding Cancer (Box-folder 2:18)
  - Episode 108: Malaria, Sickle Cell Anemia, Genes and Art (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Episode 109: Parkinson's Disease, In Cord Blood, Interstitial: Genetic News Update, Cloning Around (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Episode 110: Do Twins Run In Families?, Testing Zygosity, Downs Syndrome (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Episode 111: Athletic, Therapeutic Cloning, PGD (Pre-Implantation Genetic Diagnosis) (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Episode 112: Breast Cancer/Genetic Counseling, Tissue Engineering, Depression (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Episode 113: Bioethics, Xenografts, Genes of Risk Taking (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Episode 114: Pen Genetics, Cloning 101 Perspectives, On The Move (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Episode 115: Justice DNA, Colon Cancer, Astro-Biology (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Episode 116: Dr. Clone, (perspectives), Eugenics, De-Coding Terror (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Episode 117: Talking Genes, Animal Ancestry, DNA Blues (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Episode 118: Don't Hold The Salt, Oak Tree Disease, De-Coding Malaria (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Episode 119: Super Bugs, Got Cheese, Marine Biology Lab (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Episode 120: Prostate Cancer, Attack of the Clones, Triploid Salmon (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Episode 121: First Shots, The Air War, Exploring The Possibilities (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Episode 122: Fighting Fat, Diabetes Cause and Cure, Curing By Cloning (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Episode 123: A Need To Know, DNA in the Family Tree, In The Blood (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Episode 124: Attack of the 50 Foot Genome, Green Light for Biolog, Stemming Parkinson's (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Episode 125: Cultural Diversities: Butterflies, Cultural Diversities: Lobsters: Changing Before Our Eyes (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Episode 126: Aging, The Number of Our Days, Spry Worms (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Episode 127: The Chosen Child, A Link for the Missing, Rover Redefined (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Episode 128: Tissues with Issues, Seeing Red, DNA on the Farm (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Episode 129: Genes & Tonic, A Turn-Off for Men, Perfect Pitch (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Episode 130: A Cure for Millions, For Personal Use Only, Fighting Genes (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Episode 131: Food Fight, Going Bananas, Drugs Downsized (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Episode 132: Wiggling the Paw, Deafness in the Balance, Cancer - Compiling the Catalogue (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Episode 133: Got Silk?, Who Let the Clones Out, When You Grow Up (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Episode 134: Of Mice and a Man, Getting Under Your Skin, Mapping the Mutts (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Episode 135: Genes on Ice, Night of the Twisted Helix, Using a Killer to Cure (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Episode 136: Fugu Guru, Fighting the Fudge Fungus, Risk Factor (Box-folder 6:7)
  - Episode 137: Cream of the Clones, Array of Life, Raising the Stakes (Box-folder 6:8)
  - Episode 138: A Copy, Right?, The Case of the Missing Gene, Bypassing Bunny (Box-folder 6:9)
  - Episode 139: Skin Deep?, Offbeat Gene, Mother Tongue (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Episode 140: Apple a Day, Schizophrenia: Thought Control?, GFP, The Guiding Glow (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Episode 141: Running on Empty, From Slime to Sublime, Daughters of Eve (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Episode 142: The Case of the Bad Hives, The Double's Double Helix, Identical Twins - Opposite Sex? (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Episode 143: Of Monarchs and Milkweed, One Hundred Birthdays and Still Ticking, Built to Last (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Episode 144: Genetic Insight (MAC DEGEN), Genetic Obsessions (OCD), Lab of the Future (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Episode 145: Genetic Comb-Over, Longer Life for Livers, Salt of the Earth (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Episode 146: Rhythm and Snooze, The Viking Code, Decanting DNA (Box-folder 7:8)
  - Episode 147: Mapping Mickey, It's All in Your Head, Are the Voices in the Genes? (Box-folder 8:1)
  - Episode 148: What If? A World Without Code, Send in the Marine, Heal Thyself (Box-folder 8:2)
  - Episode 149: The Secret of Life, The Future Writ Small, A Knock-Out for Science, Deadly Patterns (Box-folder 8:3)
  - Episode 150: Gene Huggers, Sugar Rays, Will Congress Close Down Cloning? (Box-folder 8:4)
  - Episode 151: Brain Biochip, Quick Fix, Patent Pending (Box-folder 8:5)
  - Episode 152: Patients to Wait, Johnny's Genes, Clean Genes (Box-folder 8:6)
  - Personal releases (Box-folder 8:7-10)
  - Logo releases (Box-folder 8:11)
  - Music cue sheets (Box-folder 8:12)
  - Location release (Box-folder 9:1-2)
  - Stills and slides (Box-folder 9:3)
  - Stock footage releases (Box-folder 9:4-5)
  - Show EDLs (Box-folder 9:6-7)
- Videos, 2000-2003 (Box 10-52)
  Please click here for an inventory of the videos in this series.
  - Masters and submasters (Box 10-15)
  - B-roll footage (Box 16-52)